Guide to Community Service Organization History Project records M1669
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Community Service Organization. History Project records
1955-2009
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Community Service Organization.
M1669
6 Linear Feet (10 boxes)
The Community Service Organization History Project papers includes oral history interviews and other media as well as files from the CSO itself, especially pertaining to its Bakersfield Chapter, 1955-2002.
Historical Note
The Community Service Organization was an important California Latino civil rights organization, most famous for training Cesar Chavez. It was founded in 1948 by Fred Ross, Antonio Rios and Edward Roybal to empower immigrants through such programs such as voter registration drives, citizenship classes, lawsuits and legislative campaigns.
The Community Service Organization focused on voter registration drives, citizenship classes, lawsuits and legislative campaigns. The chapters of the CSO also created and ran substance abuse treatment programs, college scholarships, summer camps, death benefit societies and credit unions. CSO also created substance abuse treatment programs, college scholarships and credit unions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 2009 and 2013. Accession 2009-081 and 2013-195.
Access to Collection
Open for research. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Scope and Content
15 oral history interviews: 13 DVDs, 2005-2009; Fred Ross memorial: 2 DVDs, 1992; "The Leadership Lessons of the CSO": 3 DVDs. Files pertaining to the history project, 1997-2009. Files primarily pertaining to the Bakersfield Chapter of the CSO, 1955-2002.
Bakersfield Chapter materials include correspondence, Committee reports, financial reports, memorandums, Board Meeting minutes and agendas, newsletters, newspaper clippings, photographs, member lists, and by-laws.
Community Service Organization.
- Return to Sponsors 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 1995 Street Fair - Sponsors (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Street Fair Flyers (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 1995 Street Fair - Correnspondence (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1995 Street Fair - Press Release (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 1995 Street Fair - Vendor's Addresses (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 1995 Street Fair - Vendors (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 1995 Street Fair - Working Papers (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letters for Baher St Merchants (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 1995 Street Fair - Thank You Letters (Box 1, Folder 10)
- 1995 Street Fair - Application for Permits, etc. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- IRS (Box 1, Folder 12)
- CSO General Membership (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Citizenship Class Sign-In Shets, 10/1/96 to 4/29/97 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Community Services Organization - Father's Day Festival (Box 1, Folder 15)
- City of Bakersfield Consolidated Plan (Box 1, Folder 16)
- County of Kern Annual Action Plan (Box 1, Folder 17)
- 1994 Street Fair - Newsletters (Box 1, Folder 18)
- 1994 Street Fair - Vendors (Box 1, Folder 19)
- 1994 Street Fair - Invitations (Box 1, Folder 20)
- 1994 Street Fair - Sponsors (Box 1, Folder 21)
- 1994 Street Fair - Special Permits, Licenses, Police and Insurance (Box 1, Folder 22)
- 1994 Street Fair - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 23)
- 1995 Street Fair - Health Permit (Box 2, Folder 1)
- 1995 Income and Expense (Box 2, Folder 2)
- 1994 Father's Day (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "Good Neighbor" (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Old Town Kern 1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Old Town Kern Artsfest - October 12, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Community Service Organization - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Station KWAC - Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Various Unfinished Cases (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Various Legal Documents (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Grant - Deed (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Unfinished Cases (Box 2, Folder 12)
- KWAC Affidavits (Box 2, Folder 13)
- KWAC Renewal Licenses (Box 2, Folder 14)
- KWAC Project Information (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Invoices 1996 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- 1996 Street Fair - Forms (applications, liability release) (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Vendor's Application for Space 1996 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- 1996 Street Fair - Thank You (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Substance Abuse Program: Financial Reports, Agreements (Box 2, Folder 20)
- 1995 and 1996 State CSO Minutes (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Applications, Forms 1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Carlos Montes (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence - to file (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Membership List 1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- CSO State Chapter Roster (Box 3, Folder 6)
- 1996 Street Fair - Letter of Introduction for Donations (Box 3, Folder 7)
- 1996 Street Fair - Sponsors (Box 3, Folder 8)
- 1996 Street Fair - Letters to Sponsors (Box 3, Folder 9)
- 1996 Street Fair - Letters to Vendors (Box 3, Folder 10)
- 1996 Street Fair - Vendor Application Forms (Box 3, Folder 11)
- 1996 Street Fair - Permits and Business Tax Certificate (Box 3, Folder 12)
- 1996 Street Fair - Applications for Temporary Food Facility Certificate (Box 3, Folder 13)
- 1996 Street Fair - Press Release (Box 3, Folder 14)
- 1997 Assigned Spaces (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Invoices 1997 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- 1997 Street Fair Minutes (Box 3, Folder 17)
- 1997 Food Permits (Box 3, Folder 18)
- CSO Street Fair - 1997 Sponsor (forms) (Box 3, Folder 19)
- CSO Street Fair - 1997 Vendors (forms) (Box 3, Folder 20)
- 1997 Street Fair - Permits (Box 3, Folder 21)
- 1996 and 1997 Street Fair Sponsors (Box 3, Folder 22)
- 1997 Street Fair Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Public Service Announcements 1997 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- 1998 Street Fair Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Baker Street Fair (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Street Fair Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 2)
- CSO Clippings (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Voter Registration and Get Out the Vote (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Saints Funeral Home Plan (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Toys and Price List (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Old Town - Kern (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Board of Trade (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Downtown Business Association Bylaws (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Looking Good Neighborhood (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Sample By-Laws (Box 4, Folder 11)
- CSO Program Review (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Treasurer's Report (Box 4, Folder 13)
- CSO YCCIP Invoice 1979 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Title III Contracts, 1-1-79 to 9-30-79 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- CETA Title II (D) Subgrants (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Employment Development Department (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Death Benefit Society, New Assessment Rates (Box 4, Folder 18)
- De Colores - Director Reports (Box 4, Folder 19)
- CETA Contract for Title III, Oct. 1, 1978 - Dec. 31, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Title VI Contracts, Amendment No. I (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Y. I. P. Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 22)
- CETA Personnel (Box 4, Folder 23)
- CETA Proposals Title IV (Box 4, Folder 24)
- CETA Title VI (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Title VI Projects, Amendment No. 1 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- CSO - Monitoring Reports; The People's Right to Know; Food for Thought (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Baldimore Alvarado (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Mexican Organizations and Lodges (Box 5, Folder 2)
- CSO Buyers' Club Equipment Sale (Box 5, Folder 3)
- CSO Mailing List (Box 5, Folder 4)
- CSO Board Meeting (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Minutes to be typed (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Expenses Paid Out for Student Fair 1994 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Street Fair Expenses, Drafts Only, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- CSO loan from Drug Program (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Paid Bills, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous Business Records (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Summary Translation of Birth Certificates (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Affidavit of Witness - of Identity, et al. (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Letters on File (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Street Fair (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Kern County Hispanic Chamber of Commerce (Box 5, Folder 16)
- City of Bakersfield Site Plan Review (Box 5, Folder 17)
- CSO Disc CDBG 1994 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Mediation Committee (Box 5, Folder 19)
- M1 - M2 Zone Site Review Plan (Box 5, Folder 20)
- State Board Meeting, Sept. and March, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Father's Day Festival (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Community Development Block Grant Program (CDBG) (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Proposition 187 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Booths, Father's Day Festival (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Community Service Organization - The People's Right to Know: Excessive Force (Box 6, Folder 1)
- City of Bakersfield: Baker Street Corridor Study and Action Plan (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Original Board Minutes 1995 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Community Service Organization - The People's Right to Know: Anti-Immigrant Violence (Box 6, Folder 3)
- CSO 1996 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- State Board Meetings 1997 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- CSO Board Meetings 1997 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- 1998 Sponsor's/Vendor's List (Box 6, Folder 8)
- 1998 Street Fair - Sponsor's Response (Box 6, Folder 9)
- 1998 Street Fair - Vendor's Response (Box 6, Folder 10)
- 1998 Street Fair - Permits and Business Tax Certificates (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Baker Street Fair 1998, CSO Misc. Forms (Box 6, Folder 12)
- 1998 News Release/Public Announcement (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 14)
- CSO Pledges - Henry martinez Building Fund (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Baker Street Fair Poster, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Street Fair Procedures: 1995, 1996, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- 5th Annual Street Fair Drawing Tickets, #01 to #1,200, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- 2 VHS cassettes, 1994 and 1995 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter. Accession 2013-195, 1958-1978 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes: By-Laws of CSO's Death Benefit Society, youth reports, materials on the Kern County Conference on Youth Participation in Community Affairs, Chapter reports, Candidate Day Committee Reports, list of members and brochure for the Rosicrucian Science Museum and Planetarium. Also includes correspondence from the office of California Attorney General, Edmund Brown.
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  Includes meeting minutes, agendas, correspondence, reports and financial statements.
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1985-1986 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195 (part 1 of 2), 1993 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  Materials are from a binder labeled, "Margaret Govea".
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195 (part 2 of 2), 1993 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Board Meetings. Accession 2013-195, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  Includes Board Meeting minutes, agendas, memorandums, CSO employee policy handbook, and Substance Abuse Program Board Meeting minutes.
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Constitution, By-Laws and Parliamentary Authority. Accession 2013-195, 1983-1994 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Correspondence (1956-1965). Accession 2013-195, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  Materials primarily consist of photocopies of David Burciaga and Cesar Chavez correspondence with Local, State and Federal government agencies and politicians. Includes letters from Congressman Harlan Hagen from Californi and Adlai Stevenson. One of the items is stamped, "Reproductions. The Collections of Archives of Labor and Urban Affairs, University Archives, Wayne State University".
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Correspondence - Incoming. Accession 2013-195, 1972-1979 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  Correspondence with local, state and federal government agencies and politicians, local organizations, and colleges. Also includes memorandums, list of members, materials on the De Colores and Substance Abuse Programs, financial statements, reports and Executive Board Meetings.
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Education. Accession 2013-195, 1991-1993 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  Materials include, Kern County High School District Board of Trustees' agenda, materials for the Kern County Education Summit and Kern County School Board District map with voting totals.
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Grievance Committee Reports. Accession 2013-195, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Kern County. Accession 2013-195, 1973, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Manny Alva Realty Narrative Market Analysis. Accession 2013-195, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Manuel Marin and Program. Accession 2013-195, 1962, 1983-1994 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  Includes CSO Bakersfield Chapter Board meeting minutes, Substance Abuse Program reports and various newsletters.
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Miscellaneous. Accession 2013-195, 1955-1957 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  Materials include, Installation of Officers booklet, United Steelworkers of America's Human Relations Reporter, newspaper clippings, letter about membership dues, correspondence and a California Senate Resolution.
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Miscellaneous. Accession 2013-195, 1957-1997 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  Material include, correspondence about the CSO's Death Benefit Society, City of Bakersfield Council Agenda, correspondence, members mailing lists, Baker Street Street Faire, a report on antibiotics, CSO Board Meeting minutes, newspaper clippings, photocopies of Ahora, newsletters, a letter from the United Farm Workers of America, and the Report on Bakersfield Chapter to the State Convention,
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Miscellaneous. Accession 2013-195, 1960-1994 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  Materials include, NAACP Freedom Award citation, newsletters, newspaper clippings, photographs, and Kern County Proclamation of CSO Day.
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Newspaper clippings. Accession 2013-195, 1963-2002 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Press releases about the United Farm Workers of America. Accession 2013-195, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 13)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Report for the Sixth Annual Convention. Accession 2013-195, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Resolutions and proposals. Accession 2013-195, 1993-1994 (Box 9, Folder 15)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Tenant Improvement project manual. Accession 2013-195, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 16)
- CSO Bakersfield Chapter: Youth Conference. Accession 2013-195, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- CSO Los Angeles Chapter: Camp Seniel Ostrow. Accession 2013-195, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- CSO National. Accession 2013-195, 1962-1995 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  Materials include, Special Officers' Meeting minutes discussing Cesar Chavez leaving CSO as well as a History of the CSO brochure.
- CSO State Board Meeting. Accession 2013-195, 1975-1976 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- CSO State Convention. Accession 2013-195, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  Materials include, resolutions, agendas, reports on the regional councils, meeting minutes and financial statements.
- CSO State Convention. Accession 2013-195, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- CSO State and National: Publicity. Accession 2013-195, 1956-1957 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- CSO Stockton Chapter. Accession 2013-195, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  Includes a letter from California Governor Edmund Brown.
- Hector Tarango Compact Disc. Accession 2013-195, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Organize! The Lessons of the Community Service Organization. Accession 2013-195, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  Includes a CD and a DVD.
- Report to CSO Chapters on Memberships Paid. Accession 2013-195, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- 5 Year Strategic Plan. Accession 2013-195, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 12)